It
says starting. Yeah.
Okay, one second. That's going up. I have to adjust the height.
I am slightly taller than the ראש ישיבה. Rosh Yeshiva. Okay.
Good morning. Today's דף daf will be זבחים Zevachim דף ע"ה, daf
ayin hey, 75. But we are starting on
ע"ד עמוד ב', ayin daled amud bet, about halfway down where it
says הרובע והנרבע. haroveiah v'hanirba. And today is June 26th, the 13th
of תמוז. Tammuz. And it's Tuesday. Good.
So our משנה mishna had discussed—it's good, it's good.
I think it should be good.
Tuesday... you're missing the reference. I got the reference, I'm just not—I
didn't have anything more to say. Okay, so our משנה mishna had
discussed the case of animals getting mixed up with each other, which
is exactly what we're continuing to discuss here. And the משנה mishna
had a long list of many different types of animals who are
פסול pasul to be brought as קרבנות korbanot for a variety of
reasons. רובע roveiah and נרבע nirba are cases where the animal either
played the male or female role in an act of bestiality, and
there are many others listed in the משנה mishna as well.
Here, I'm trying to go back to actually where it is in
the משנה. mishna. I think this is the משנה mishna on ע"ב,
ayin bet, right?
Sorry, I was in the wrong spot,
no, ע"א. ayin aleph. ע"א עמוד ב'. ayin aleph amud bet. And
the משנה mishna says, right?
Basically
all of these different animals, רובע ונרבע, roveiah v'nirba, מוקצה—מוקצה is something
that was set aside to be used for עבודה זרה avodah zarah
but was not worshipped—ונעבד, v'ne'evad, or an animal which was worshipped itself.
ואתנן—אתנן זונה is a prohibition in the תורה; Torah; אתנן etnan means
something you give to a prostitute to pay for her
services—ומחיר כלב, u'mechir kelev, an animal which was used—its value, the animal
was used as the purchasing power to buy a dog. That's just
explicit in the תורה. Torah. There's a whole question about what does
that actually mean, but that's what the הלכה halacha is. ובכלאים, u'bekilayim,
and an animal which is a crossbreed—you could imagine a crossbreed of
sheep with wild sheep and goats with wild goats and all different
kinds of things—or sheep with sheep? It depends on exactly which kind
of species. There's a whole מסכת כלאים masechet kilayim about it, you
ask Charlie about it, he's studied it more recently than I have.
ובטרפה, u'vetreifa, and a טרפה treifa is an animal which has undergone
an injury. We'll discuss it at great length in מסכת חולין, masechet
chullin, all of the different rules of טרפה, treifa, and Rabbi Linzer
has much to say about טרפה. treifa. But our סוגיא sugia now
is going to be interested primarily in the question of a טרפה.
treifa. That is, the גמרא gemara says, בשלמא כולהו—so bishlama kulhu most
of these animals on this list, I understand how the case could
arise. Some animal has some non-physical issue, it
was used in a certain way, there was a certain sin done
with this animal or something like that, so לא ידיע, lo yadia,
I don't know which animal is which. So if it gets mixed
in with a whole flock of other sheep or something, then that's
where the problem is going to occur. אלא האי טרפה היכי דמי?
ela hai treifa heichi dami? What case is there of טרפה? treifa?
How can I have a טרפה treifa animal which presumably has undergone
some serious injury which I now am aware of and yet now
how did I lose it? If it was so injured that it's
a טרפה, treifa, then
how can I not identify it once it got mixed in with
the others?
So we have three different answers of the אמוראים, amoraim, and we're
going to see why—and there are basically no resolution given in the
גמרא. gemara. Each of them has their own leg to stand on,
it's connected to other מחלוקות. machlokot. Leg to stand on? No, leg
to stand—oh goodness, a טרפה, treifa, right? אוי געוואלד. oy gevald. אמרי
דבי
רבי ינאי: amri de-bei Rabbi Yannai: so the school of רבי ינאי
Rabbi Yannai quoted from רבי ינאי Rabbi Yannai's teaching, הכא במאי עסקינן,
hacha b'mai askinan, the case we're talking about, כגון דעירב ניקובת הקוץ
בדרוסת הזאב. kegon de-irav nikuvat hakotz b'drusat haze'ev. The case where no,
that there are two different types of animals with injuries that have
gotten mixed up. One is ניקובת הקוץ, nikuvat hakotz, was punctured by
a thorn, which in all likelihood has not pierced the inner organs
in any way and caused any substantial injury and therefore the animal
will not be a טרפה, treifa, בדרוסת הזאב, b'drusat haze'ev, with an
animal that was attacked by a wolf. An animal that was attacked
by a wolf, there's much higher likelihood that the internal organs were
damaged and that it has become a טרפה. treifa. So according to
רבי ינאי, Rabbi Yannai, you could see the animal with the same
outward injury could still one be a טרפה treifa and one not.
That's his—I'm also thinking a דרוסת הזאב drusat haze'ev is not like
one little teeny puncture mark, you know.
Ah, so the גמרא gemara will explain why the other אמוראים amoraim
do not agree with רבי ינאי, Rabbi Yannai, in part of the
reason is even in the particular puncture wound will actually look different,
right? If you imagine a wolf biting with its teeth, there'll be
a more elongated puncture, which is exactly what the גמרא—and gemara it
had more
than one tooth presumably.
And more than one tooth, right? I remember when our veterinarian told
me something about... our dog was attacked by another dog once, he
had a little bite, and the veterinarian said whenever there's a bite,
there always have to be two wounds because there has to be
an upper jaw and the lower jaw. So it's an interesting thing
I had never thought of how to identify a bite wound before,
but it's exactly correct. Okay, the second opinion is ריש לקיש. Reish
Lakish. ריש לקיש Reish Lakish אמר amar כגון k'gon דאיתערב d'it'arev בנפולה.
bin'fulah. So the טריפה treifa animal has been mixed with a נפולה,
nefulah, an animal which fell down. It fell off the roof, it
fell, right, I've been teaching בבא קמא, Bava Kamma, so there's a
case the sheep fell into the garden, right? That's a little bit
of a different case, but בנפולה. bin'fulah. נפולה nefulah נמי nami לבדקיה.
livd'kei. So then you should just be able to check this animal
whether it's really a טריפה treifa or not. You can let it
sit for a few days or whatever you can examine it after
the שחיטה, shechita, you'll be able to find out whether or not
it was a טריפה. treifa. So it won't be such a problem.
קסבר Kasavar עמדה, amda, so but it must be that ריש לקיש
Reish Lakish is of the opinion that if it stands up after
it was injured, that is if it regains its full mobility, צריכה
tsricha מעת לעת, me-et le-et,
that it still needs to wait twenty-four hours before to confirm that
it's not seriously injured. הלכה, Halcha, and if it even if it
is able to walk afterwards, צריכה בדיקה. tzerichah bedikah, Then even after
it's שחט, shachted, you still need to check whether it's a טריפה
treifa or not. Generally nowadays for חולין chullin animals we check basically
every animal to see if it's a טריפה. treifa. We'll see in
מסכת חולין Masechet Chullin that the standards, at least להלכה, l'halacha, the
standards may be lower than what are currently practiced in the slaughterhouses.
Obviously slaughterhouses have to have good, good practices in general. But the
assumption of every animal is that we assume it has a חזקת
כשרות. chazkat kashrut. We don't assume that it's a טריפה. treifa. So
you would need some reason to assume that it had undergone an
injury, and if by the time it was נפלה ועמדה nafla v'amda
and you had מעת לעת, me-et le-et, already at that point, then
according to ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, even if הלכה, halcha, even if
it was able to walk again after this fall, צריכה tsricha בדיקה,
bdika. it needs to be checked. So that would be why ריש
לקיש Reish Lakish could understand that an animal that was actually a
טריפה treifa could have easily gotten mixed up with animals which were
not טריפות treifot because the burden of proof has now become to
check after the שחיטה. shechita. רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiya אמר, amar, third
opinion of the אמוראים, Amoraim, of all three from ארץ ישראל, Eretz
Yisrael, also interesting. So רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiya אמר amar כגון k'gon
דאיתערב d'it'arev בוולד טריפה. bivlad treifa. The טריפה treifa animal was intermixed
with or, or what we're talking about actually is not a טריפה
treifa animal itself which had the injury, but ולד טריפה, vlad treifa,
the animal which was born from a mother who was herself a
טריפה. treifa. Charlie has a question.
I'm reminded of the experiment where they delivered a healthy
fetus, a healthy infant from the decapitated sheep.
Right, it
wasn't just a טריפה, treifa, it was
actually, yeah, so from a dead בן פקועה ben pekua cases, etc.
So there are many different things. Part of the problem, and this
is discussed extensively, I think, by some of the ראשונים Rishonim is
the question of whether a טריפה treifa animal will actually ever be
able to be pregnant and carry the pregnancy to term because, and
these are sort of the questions about, right? So and part of
these questions about whether טריפה treifa is a formal definition or טריפה
treifa is really just an estimation of whether the animal has a
severe injury and which types of injuries. You know, many of the
things that we think of as טריפות treifot maybe in, you know,
the whole issue of the question, controversies around the milk are issues
about maybe there's something which formally makes the cow a טריפה treifa
which the cow is perfectly happy to survive with that injury long-term.
So it does raise certain questions. I know Rabbi Linzer has some
שיעורים shiurim about that. רמב"ם's Rambam approach based on ירושלמי Yerushalmi and
other things. But anyway, so how do we know
that it's a טריפה treifa to begin with?
That's exactly the problem. The problem is if you knew it was
a טריפה treifa to begin with, then how did it get mixed
up? And if it got mixed up, how do you know it's
a טריפה? treifa? So that's the whole issue here. That's exactly what
these three opinions of the אמוראים Amoraim are trying to explain is
basically all three of
them. So רבי ינאי's Rabbi Yannai position is that it is a
טריפה treifa animal and I knew it was a טריפה treifa animal
but it could have got mixed up anyway because the other animals
also had injuries,
נקובה בקוץ בדרוסת הזאב. Nikuva be-kotz bi-drusat ha-ze'ev. Okay. ריש לקיש's Reish
Lakish position, something similar. There's an animal which has now an unknown
status injury and it has gotten mixed up with other animals. So
I know which animal it is but I don't know whether it's
a טריפה treifa or not. And רבי ינאי's Rabbi Yannai position is
actually that this animal is a ולד טריפה, vlad treifa, so it
has some of the status of טריפה, treifa, at least it has
the disqualification of טריפה, treifa, but there's no way to physically identify
it because it doesn't have an injury.
But then doesn't it sort of take away from our משנה? Mishna?
So yeah, of course כולן ימותו kulan imatu because what are you
going to do? They're all טריפות treifot anyway and like what else
are you going to do?
But they're not all טריפות treifot anyway. That's the point.
What do you mean? נקובה בקוץ בדרוסת הזאב, Nikuva be-kotz bi-drusat ha-ze'ev,
they're both טריפות. treifot.
No, meaning one of them is a טריפה treifa and one of
them isn't and I don't know which one is which. So what?
We're saying
דרוסת הזאב drusat ha-ze'ev is not a טריפה?
treifa? דרוסת הזאב Drusat ha-ze'ev is, is a טריפה. treifa. נקובה בקוץ,
Nikuva be-kotz, I imagine you have a tiny little thorn punctures the
skin, so I know there's an injury on this animal, but I
don't know, I presume that it still has not become injured in
such a way that it's actually a טריפה, treifa, it just has
an injury. There's an injury and there's an injury which causes a
which makes it a טריפה. treifa.
Okay, wait, where was it? That is,
oh, wait, so it's נתערבו nit'arvu in all these טריפה. treifa. So
we're saying we have something that's maybe a טריפה treifa got mixed
up with definitely a טריפה? treifa? Is that what you're saying? Or
not?
At this point, maybe a טריפה treifa at least for now we're
going to assume is not a טריפה. treifa. This kind of נקיבת
הקוץ nikuvat hakotz is such a minor injury that it's not, we
don't even have a concern that it's a טריפה, treifa, but the
injury looks similar enough that we're worried that it got mixed up
with an animal that was a טריפה. treifa. So now the גמרא
Gemara is going to explain. Okay,
sorry, one second, we were in the middle of the ולד טריפה
ורבי אליעזר היא vlad treifa ve-Rabbi Eliezer hi and רבי ירמיהו'ס Rabbi
Yirmiyahu's position is within רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer דאמר ולד טריפה לא
יקרב לגבי המזבח de'amar vlad treifa lo yikarev legabei hamizbe'ach even that
the ולד טריפה vlad treifa is disqualified from the from bringing as
a קרבן. korban. כולהו כרבי ינאי לא אמרי. Kulhu ke-Rabbi Yannai lo
amri. So why do ריש לקיש Resh Lakish and רבי ירמיה Rabbi
Yirmiyah not agree with רבי ינאי? Rabbi Yannai? בין נקיבת הקוץ לדרוסת
הזאב מידע ידיע. Bein nikuvat hakotz ledrusat haze'ev meda yadiah. It's, if
you can identify the differences in the injury between if it was
punctured by a thorn and if it was attacked by a wolf.
So האי משיך והאי עגיל. Hai mashich vehai agil. One is a
drawn elongated puncture. The wolf is tearing at the animal, so it'll
be elongated. והאי עגיל, Vehai agil, and the puncture from a thorn
will be just a circular puncture.
This is discussed, comes up, the question of משוך ועגול mashuch ve-agul
also comes up in the discussions of כתמים ketamim in הלכות נדה
Hilchot Niddah about whether the whether the כתם ketem is is a
drop of of from smooshing a bug or whether it's משוך, mashuch,
it's elongated, so some of that comes up there and generally we're
not so מחמיר machmir to try to distinguish between them.
Okay,
כריש לקיש לא אמרי. Ke-Resh Lakish lo amri. So why do רבי
ינאי Rabbi Yannai and רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiyah not agree with ריש
לקיש? Resh Lakish? קסברי עמדה אינה צריכה מעת לעת הלכה אינה צריכה
בדיקה Kasvari amda einah tzerichah me'et le'et, halcha einah tzerichah bedikah because
they פסק'ן pasken the more more מקיל meikel position that if the
animal fell down, you actually don't need to to test it out
for 24 hours or to test it out, check it afterwards to
see. Basically you assume if it was able to stand up again
and and walk again that it's not a טריפה treifa and you
don't have to examine it. And כרבי ירמיה לא אמרי. Ke-Rabbi Yirmiyah
lo amri. So why did ריש לקיש... Resh Lakish why did רבי
Rebbe, ינאי and ריש לקיש Resh Lakish, not agree with רבי ירמיה?
Rabbi Yirmiyah? So because כרבי אליעזר לא מוקמי. ke-Rabbi Eliezer lo mukmi.
They don't hold like רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer.
So it makes perfect sense.
Everybody has a good reason for their own opinion and everybody else
has good reasons not to agree with the other opinions. Yes.
You've seen that that if an animal fell from a roof, it
could have sustained internal injuries. Why wouldn't they require that after they
slaughter?
Because remember what we're saying. If it was עמדה, amda, if it
stood up.
That's a sign.
Then that's a sign that it wasn't really so injured. And הלכה,
halcha, if it was able to walk again, then certainly it wasn't
so severely injured. So for ריש לקיש, Resh Lakish, ריש לקיש'ס Resh
Lakish's concern and רבי Rabbi אלי... it's sorry, that, yeah, this is
ריש לקיש'ס position based on an opinion elsewhere is
is that even if it if it demonstrates to a certain threshold
that it has not sustained a serious injury, we have to check
a little bit more anyway because now you could imagine somehow the
חזקה chazakah has changed. No longer is this animal בחזקת כשרות, be-chezkat
kashrut, now the animal sustained an injury. We don't know how severe
the injury is. So now the the burden of proof is to
demonstrate according to ריש לקיש, Resh Lakish the burden of proof is
now to demonstrate that the animal is healthy. So it has to
be עמדה צריכה מעת לעת. amda tzerichah me'et le'et. If it's able
to stand up, it needs 24 hours. הלכה, halcha, even if it's
able to walk, צריכה tsricha בדיקה, bdika, then you still need to
check afterwards. So so those phases for ריש לקיש Reish Lakish is
a because the חזקה chazakah has shifted. And the other אמוראים Amoraim
are willing to say actually no, this animal by demonstrating it's able
to stand up, it's able to walk, we don't have to assume
that it it sustained any serious injury. Okay. The משנה Mishnah had
continued קדשים בקדשים מין במינו. Kodashim be-kodashim min be-mino. So the the
principle is is that if the קרבנות korbanot of the same type
were mixed together, right? The משנה Mishnah says קדשים בקדשים מין במינו
זה יקרב לשם מי שהוא וזה יקרב לשם מי שהוא. Kodashim be-kodashim
min be-mino, zeh yikarev leshem mi shehu vezeh yikarev leshem mi shehu.
So if I let's say you know three different people were bringing
קרבן חטאת korban chatat and or קרבן חטאת korban chatat is a
bad example, three different people bring קרבן עולה korban olah and
but now the they've gotten mixed up so I don't know which
animal was brought by which owner. So the כהן kohen will have
in mind that this עולה olah is for this person and is
for whomever owns it, not for this person specifically but it's for
whomever owns it. So sort of a general catch-all kind of מחשבה.
machshavah. So the גמרא Gemara asks והא בעי סמיכה. Veha ba'ei semichah.
Don't you have to do סמיכה semichah on a קרבן? korban?
No, בדיעבד bedi'avad it's... Okay, so בדיעבד bedi'avad it's לא מעכב.
lo me'akev. But you have a חיוב chiyuv to do the סמיכה,
semichah, meaning how can we לכתחילה lechatchilah bring this קרבן korban in
a way which which is less than ideal?
Because they're doing it בדיעבד. bedi'avad.
Okay, so it's בדיעבד bedi'avad after they got mixed up but we're
still bringing the קרבן. korban. Anyway, that's the question.
So someone who needs to bring a קרבן korban who is unable
to travel ירושלים Yerushalayim sends it with a שליח. shaliach.
Okay right. So there are circumstances in which what at least in
this case this is the גמרא'ס Gemara's question. not an amazing question
and it's basically going to not really amount to much because it's
a setup for what's coming later. But it's yeah no I hear
it's a bad question. It's not such a good question. But אמר
רב יוסף, Amar Rav Yosef, so רב יוסף Rav Yosef says it
must be that the משנה Mishnah is speaking specifically about קרבן נשים,
korban nashim, קרבן korban brought by women because women don't do full
סמיכה, semichah, there's no requirement for women to do סמיכה, semichah, and
therefore there's no no issue there of
because the owners can't do the סמיכה semichah on the animal that
that somehow it will be less than ideal. אבל בקרבן אנשים לא,
Aval bekorban anashim la, but the משנה Mishnah is not talking about
a case of men's sacrifices. So איתיביה אביי. itvei Abaye. אביי Abaye
very often, I've noticed this over the past few months, אביי Abaye
very often challenges רב יוסף. Rav Yosef. אביי Abaye was a very
a pusher of a student. You know, we hear about ריש לקיש
and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan which of course a very similar or
even more extreme version of the same kind of a student pushing
his רבי, Rebbi but here אביי Abaye also very often challenges and
pushes רב יוסף Rav Yosef to develop his ideas further. It's very
interesting. So איתיביה אביי, itvei Abaye, אביי Abaye challenged
רב יוסף: Rav Yosef: קרבן יחיד שנתערב בקרבן יחיד ובקרבן ציבור שנתערב
בקרבן ציבור. Korban yachid shenitarev bekorban yachid, ube-korban tzibbur shenitarev bekorban tzibbur.
So if an individual's קרבן korban was intermixed with another individual's קרבן,
korban, or a קרבן korban of the community was intermixed with a
communal
קרבן, korban, וקרבן יחיד וקרבן ציבור שנתערבו זה בזה, ve-korban yachid ve-korban
tzibbur shenitarvu zeh bazeh, or a personal and public קרבן korban which
mixed together, נותן ארבע מתנות מכל אחד ואחד. noten arba matanot mikkol
echad ve-echad. Because we're concerned maybe there was one קרבן חטאת korban
chatat in this mixture or whatever, which חלילה chalila we should try
to do from the blood of each קרבן korban to put all
four מתנות matanot on all four קרנות המזבח. karnot hamizbe'ach. ואם נתן
מתנה מכל אחד יצא. Ve'im natan matanah mikkol echad yatza. So if
you and if you ended up doing only one מתנה matanah from
each קרבן, korban, then בדיעבד bedi'eved that's okay, because that's the same
דין din we know by חטאת chatat that even a חטאת chatat
if you were only gave one מתנה matanah בדיעבד bedi'eved it's also
kosher. ואם נתן ארבע מכולן יצא. Ve'im natan arba mikkullan yatza. And
if you the blood got mixed together and you ended up only
doing one מתנה matanah from from all the blood mixed together, even
four מתנות, matanot, that's also...
wait, so it says נתן ארבע מכולן? natan arba mikkullan?
ארבע מכולן, Arba mikkullan, that is, you made four מתנות matanot of
the intermixed blood of all of the קרבנות korbanot together.
Okay, right. So it's you
did four
מתנות.
matanot. Well, I said you did one מתנה. matanah.
No, meaning, the middle case was...
no no no, the last case.
Yeah, the last case is ארבע מכולן, arba mikkullan, four, but the
blood was mixed together. So the first case is from each קרבן
korban individually you did four מתנות matanot out of the ספק. safek.
That's what you should do. בדיעבד Bedi'eved if you did only one
מתנה matanah from each קרבן korban individually, then you are יוצא, yotzei,
and even if the blood got all mixed together and you were
only able to do four מתנות matanot of the blood all mixed
together, then you are also יוצא. yotzei. So אביי, Abaye, we still
don't exactly understand אביי's Abaye question
yet. So אביי Abaye is now explaining. במה דברים אמורים, Bemei devarim
amurim, what was this ברייתא baraita talking about? שנתערבו חיים. Shenitarvu chayyim.
If the animals got mixed up while they were alive. אבל נתערבו
שחוטים, Aval nitarvu shechutin, if they were mixed up after they had
been slaughtered, נותן ארבע מתנות מכולן. noten arba matanot mikkullan. You have
to give four מתנות matanot from every animal,
ואם נתן מתנה אחת מכולן יצא. ve'im natan matanah achat mikkullan yatza.
And if you give one מתנה matanah from all of the blood
mixed together, then that's also יוצא. yotzei. So slightly different rules for
how the מתנות matanot work if they were mixed up, if the
blood was mixed after they were shechted or if the animals were
mixed before they were shechted. רבי אומר, Rabbi omer, רבי Rebbi says,
רואין את המתנה אם יש בה כדי לזה וכדי לזה. ro'in et
hamatanah im yesh bah kedei lazeh u-kedei lazeh. We see if the
amount of blood that was put on the מזבח mizbe'ach has enough
quantity that it has enough that it could contain the blood from
from all the different animals. כשרה. Kesherah. Then it will be כשרה.
kesherah. ואם לאו פסולה. Ve'im lav pesulah. If it's small enough a
quantity of blood that there's not enough that it has blood from
each one or or that it count could count as a מתנה
matanah from each one, then פסולה. pesulah. By the way, this is
kind of seemingly connected to the מחלוקת machloket between רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda about whether we say מין במינו
בטל min bemino batel or not. Opinion of רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda,
especially in the case of blood, he uses blood as the example
based on the עבודה avodah of יום כיפורים, Yom Kippurim, that מין
במינו אינו בטל. min bemino eino batel. If the two of the
same substance, blood mixed with blood or something like that, are mixed
together, then they're not we don't they don't cancel each other. So
they retain their identity. So here we have the blood of this
קרבן korban and the blood of this קרבן korban and the blood
of this קרבן korban and they were all mixed together, but they're
you're still able to fulfill the מצוה mitzvah of of the מתנות
matanot for each קרבן. korban. They're not treated as independent substances. רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon has to agree by certain cases, maybe even רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon would agree in this case, but it's at least
somewhat connected to that מחלוקת. machloket. Okay. So now אביי's Abaye question:
קתני יחיד. Katani yachid. So this ברייתא baraita deals with a case
of יחיד. yachid. דומיא דציבור. Dumya detzibbur. A case of an individual
which is similar to the public.
מה ציבור גברא... Mah tzibbur gavra... communal קרבנות korbanot which are paid
for by the שקלים shekalim which are donated by men, and therefore
the ציבור, tzibbur, representative of the ציבור, tzibbur, represented by the קרבנות
korbanot are as if owned by men. אף יחיד גברי, Af yachid
gavrei, so then we should also be talking about a case of
a קרבן יחיד korban yachid which is owned by a man and
therefore רב יוסף's Rav Yosef אוקימתא. ukimta. That's interesting.
So women aren't like covered by the קרבן תמיד? korban tamid?
It's not like they don't contribute to it? That's a question about
מסכת שקלים. Masechet Shekalim. Women, if I remember correctly, women are allowed
to donate שקלים shekalim but it's not mandatory, if I remember correctly.
But nevertheless, doesn't the קרבן korban cover all בני ישראל? Bnei Yisrael?
Of course.
So the question of how that works and how it's operative and
how we as modern readers relate to those questions are interesting questions.
But how is it a קרבן ציבור גברי? korban tzibbur gavrei? It's
not.
קרבן ציבור korban tzibbur is everyone. Okay, a קרבן ציבור korban tzibbur
is not גברי gavrei as... right, so that's part of the point.
Is a קרבן ציבור korban tzibbur is the ציבור? tzibbur? Who cares
who paid for it? Fundamentally, it is brought by the corporate entity
of בני ישראל. Bnei Yisrael. That's something we discussed at length in
מסכת הוריות Masechet Horayot and things like that. How does the ציבור
tzibbur operate as a corporation? How does the ציבור tzibbur operate as
a collection of individuals?
Right, no. Okay. So this is אביי's Abaye way of reading that
issue. Certainly, there are other ways to read it. So maybe רב
יוסף Rav Yosef has a good answer to this. But at least
the way אביי Abaye asks the question. Okay. So אמר רבא, Amar
Rava, so רבא Rava says, ותסברא המסתייעא היא. ve-tisbera hamistaya hi.
So רבא Rava thinks exactly that this ברייתא baraita supports רב יוסף,
Rav Yosef, not contradicts. Okay. דקתני במה דברים אמורים, de-katani ba-meh devarim
amurim, because what does the ברייתא baraita say? What are we talking
about? במה דברים אמורים כשנתערבו חיים, ba-meh devarim amurim keshe-nitarvu chayyim, the
animals were mixed while they were alive. אבל נתערבו שחוטים, Aval nitarvu
shechutim, לא. lo.
That it's not necessary. That is, you can even fulfill it with
a relatively minimal מתנה matanah if they were mixed up after they
were שחוטים shechutim and it was the דם dam that got mixed.
So מה לי חיים מה לי שחוטים? ma li chayyim ma li
shechutim? So why does it matter whether they're alive or have already
been שחוטים? shechutim? אלא הכי קאמר, ela hachi ka'amar, this is what
it means to say. This is now רבא's Rava amended version of
רבא's Rava answer. שנתערבו שחוטים כעין חיים, she-nitarvu shechutim ke-ein chayyim,
they were intermixed after they had been שחוטים shechutim but in a
way which is similar to if they were still alive. That is
בכוסות, be-kossot, the דם dam is each stored in individual containers. אבל
בבלול, Aval be-vulel, if the דם dam was all mixed together, then
נותן ארבע מתנות לכולם. noten arba matanot le-kulam. Then you just have
to put four מתנות matanot from all the mixed דם dam together.
ואם נתן מתנה אחת לכולם יצא, Ve-im natan matanah achat le-kulam yatza,
and if you did only one מתנה, matanah, then you're still יצא.
yatza. רבי אומר, Rebbi omer, now, so we've had an amended version
of the ברייתא baraita that fits רבא's Rava reading. Okay. So רבי
אומר, Rebbi omer, what does רבי Rebbi say? רואין את המתנה אם
יש בה כדי לזה וכדי לזה כשרה. ro'in et ha-matanah im yesh
bah kedei la-zeh ve-kedei la-zeh keshera. We see if it's the same
quantity enough to contain דם dam from both, then it's כשרה, keshera,
ואם לאו פסולה. ve-im lav pesula. ומי אית ליה לרבי האי סברא?
U-mi it lei le-Rebbi hai sevara? So wait a second, where does
רבי Rebbi, get this idea that the דם dam has to be
of a sufficient quantity to contain enough דם dam from each
קרבן? korban? You don't need very much דם. dam. Okay, so that's
exactly this point. והתניא, ve-ha tanya, isn't there this ברייתא? baraita? So,
and this ברייתא baraita here. Okay. אמר רבי לדברי רבי אליעזר, Amar
Rebbi le-divrei Rebbi Eliezer, so רבי says within the opinion of רבי
אליעזר, Rebbi Eliezer, and this is from the...
it comes up in the תוספתא Tosefta in פרה, Parah, I think.
Is that right?
Yes. Okay. הזיה כל שהוא מטהרת, hazaya kol she-hu metaheret, הזיה כל
שהוא מטהרת, hazaya kol she-hu metaheret, that if even a tiniest drop
of the מי חטאת, mei chatat, the water of the פרה אדומה,
parah adumah, lands on someone who is טמא tamei and who is
being purified, then even a minuscule quantity is enough. There's no such
thing as a כדי הזיה, kedei hazaya, there's no minimal quantity of
water that's necessary. That is, it just has to be even the
tiniest drop that lands on you, then you're purified. So הזיה אינה
צריכה שיעור. hazaya eina tzericha shi'ur.
So there's no minimal size. Okay. So הזיה מחצה כשר מחצה פסול?
hazaya mechtza kasher mechtza pasul? So what if it was half כשר
kasher and half disqualified? That is, somehow some of the water or
two different containers of water and one was פסול pasul and one
was כשר kasher and they're mixed together and then you got sprinkled
on it? So לדבריו דרבי אליעזר קאמר. le-divrav de-Rebbi Eliezer ka'amar. He
was saying within the opinion of רבי אליעזר. Rebbi Eliezer. ואיבעית אימא
הזיה לחוד ונתינה לחוד. ve-iba'it eima hazaya le-chud ve-netina le-chud. Maybe there's
a difference between הזיה hazaya by the case of פרה אדומה parah
adumah where the act of sprinkling... I mean, you can think about
it sort of how it atomizes the water. So even the action
that you're doing is understandably a more minimal action. You're sprinkling little
drops of water. The מתנה matanah of דם, dam, even, even for
a קרבן חטאת korban chatat where the כהן kohen has to use
his finger is still a reasonable amount. There has to be enough
דם dam to get on the קרן, keren, and certainly for any
of the שתים שהן ארבע shtayim she-hen arba where you use a
מתנה בכוס, matanah be-kos, the amount you throw it with the cup,
it's a substantial amount of דם. dam. It's not some minimal amount.
So maybe that's why רבי, even though it seems like this תוספתא
Tosefta proves against him, you could distinguish between the cases of פרה
parah and the cases of the קרבנות. korbanot. Okay. אמר רבי בר...
Amar Rebbi bar... so נתערבו בבכור ובמעשר *nitarvu bevechor uvemaaser*. The next
case in the משנה Mishnah *mishna*. Sorry, just keep having to flipping
back to the משנה Mishnah *mishna*. So the משנה Mishnah *mishna* had
said, sorry, נתערבו בבכור ובמעשר *nitarvu bevechor uvemaaser*. If animals with with
these disqualifying features were intermixed with בכור Bechor *bechor* animals which are
going to be brought basically as as a בכור Bechor *bechor*, but
as a kind of a קרבן Korban. שלמים *korban shelamim* to be
eaten by the כהנים *kohanim*, ובמעשר *uvemaaser*, or those which are which
are, you know, מעשר *maaser*, which is brought usually understood to be
brought by the ישראל *Yisrael*, the owner themselves, ירעו עד שיסתאבו *yireu
ad sheyistavu*. They have to graze until they until they develop a
מום mum? *mum*. ויאכלו כבכור וכמעשר *veyachlu kebechor uchemaaser*. And they have
to be eaten like בכור Bechor *bechor* and מעשר *maaser* which got
a מום mum *mum*. הכל יכולים להתערב חוץ מן החטאת והאשם *hakol
yecholim lehitaarev chutz min hachatas vehasham*. Everybody can get mixed up except
for חטאת Chatat *chatas* and אשם Asham *asham*, because חטאת Chatat *chatas*
and אשם *asham* have this unique connection to the owners because of
the sin that they that they're atoning for. So אמר רבי בר
חמא *amar Rabbi bar Chama*. רבי בר חמא *Rabbi bar Chama* said
בכור Bechor לבית שמאי *bechor leBeis Shammai*. According to בית שמאי Beit
Shammai *Beis Shammai*, a בכור Bechor, *bechor*, the בכור Bechor *bechor* animal
of the which goes to the כהנים *kohanim*, אין מאכילין לנידות *ein
maachilin leniddos*. You cannot feed the בכור Bechor *bechor* to a woman
who is in נידה *niddah*. That is even presumably a בכור Bechor
*bechor* which had a מום mum *mum* which became which which is
really just becomes a חולין chulin, *chullin* animal, the כהן Kohen. *kohen*
is allowed to eat it, somehow still according to בית שמאי *Beis
Shammai*, the the rule is that you can't feed it to a
woman who is in נידה *niddah* because presumably some kind of residual
קדושת בכור Kedushat Bechor, *kedushas bechor* associated with this animal is a
little bit of
it's a little bit weird. Okay. ותמורתו מהו *usmuraso mahu*? So what
about if you made a תמורה *tmurah* of a בכור Bechor *bechor*?
So בכור Bechor אינו נפדה *bechor eino nifdah*. So you're not allowed
to be פודה podeh *podeh* a בכור *bechor* animal. So תמורתו מהו
*usmuraso mahu*? So what so what am I allowed to do with
its תמורה *tmurah*? בכור אינו נשקל בליטרה *bechor eino nishkal belitra*. תמורתו
מהו *usmuraso mahu*? And and so all of these different conditions, that
is even a בכור *bechor* which developed a מום *mum* if you
made a תמורה *tmurah* of it and if a בכור *bechor* that
was not allowed to be פודה podeh *podeh* can you make a
תמורה *tmurah* of it? And בכור אינו נשקל *bechor eino nishkal*. It
can't be weighed out with a ליטרה *litra*. ליטרה *litra* is a
certain amount of money, right? Like if the,
no, like the weighing out the meat, like if the כהן *kohen*
is, sorry, I misspoke. If the כהן *kohen* has already שחט *shachted*
the בכור *bechor* and is now selling out the meat,
then you can't weigh it out in in cuts, you know, a
certain steak of בכור *bechor* meat in a certain size and weigh
it out in the marketplace. ותמורתו מהו *usmuraso mahu*? So what do
you do about the case of תמורה *tmura*? So אמר רבא תניא
*amar Rava tanya*. This is the ברייתא *braisa* according to רבא *Rava*.
בכור ומעשר שהוממו *bechor umaaser shehumemu*. בכור *bechor* and a מעשר *maaser*
that were שהוממו
*shehumemu*. Sorry, I forgot the word. Dovid? שהוממו *shehumemu*? בכור ומעשר שהוממו
*bechor umaaser shehumemu*. What's the שהוממו *shehumemu*? Sorry.
בכור ומעשר שהוממו *bechor umaaser
shehumemu*. It's on the left. בכור
ומעשר after they've become blemished.
Oh מום *mum*. Okay, fine. I was wondering there. That was the
thing. Okay, sorry. So בכור ומעשר שהוממו *bechor umaaser shehumemu*. They received
the מום *mum*. Then עושין תמורה *osin tmurah*. Then at that point
once they've got a מום *mum* then they can they can make
a תמורה *tmurah* at that point. That is if you point to
the בכור *bechor* and say I want to be ממיר *meimeir* the
קדושה Kedusha, *kedusha* onto a different animal, then it would work. Okay.
So it sounds like ותמורתן כיוצא בהן *usmurason kayotzei bahen*. And the
תמורה *tmurah* will have the same דין *din* as the בכור *bechor*
and the מעשר *maaser*. So בעי רמי בר חמא *baei Rami bar
Chama*. So רמי בר חמא *Rami bar Chama* asks רבא *Rava* the
following question: התפיס בכור לבדק הבית מהו hitpis Bechor le-Bedek HaBayit mahu?
*hitpis bechor lebedek habayis mahu*? What if I take a בכור *bechor*
animal and I try to make it into קדושת בדק הבית Bedek
HaBayit. *kedushas bedek habayis*? I try to donate its value to the
בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash*. מהו שישקול בליטרה *mahu sheyishkol belitra*? Can once
I've שחט *shachted* it can I weigh out the meat and sell
it in that way? רווחא דהקדש עדיף *ravcha dehekdesh adif*. If I
sell it at retail prices, you know in steaks, then the increase
in value I'm actually increasing the value which is being donated to
הקדש *hekdesh*, right? If I've made the בכור *bechor* into בדק הבית
Bedek HaBayit, *bedek habayis* then I'm trying to increase the value by
selling it retail I'm increasing the income that's being collected by בית
המקדש *Beis HaMikdash*.
Except how do they sell it?
Okay. או דילמא זילותא דבכור עדיף *o dilma zilusa debechor adif*. So
which is better? Do do we have competing values? We have a
competing value of רווחא דהקדש *ravcha dehekdesh*. We want to increase the
amount of money that בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash* collects and זילותא דבכור
*zilusa
debechor*. You're devaluing or you're showing disregard for the בכור *bechor* animal.
So אמר רבי יוסי בר זבידא *amar Rabbi Yosi bar Zavda*. So
רבי יוסי בר זבידא *Rabbi Yosi bar Zavda* said תא שמע נתערבו
בכור ומעשר ירעו עד שיסתאבו *ta shema nitarvu bechor umaaser yireu ad
sheyistavu*. Proof from our משנה Mishnah. *mishna*. What does our משנה Mishnah,
*mishna* say? If an animal disqualified animals were mixed with בכור ומעשר
ירעו עד שיסתאבו ויאכלו כבכור וכמעשר *bechor umaaser yireu ad sheyistavu veyachlu
kebechor uchemaaser*. So they have to graze until they develop a מום
*mum* and then you eat them like בכור *bechor* and מעשר *maaser*.
So לאו למימרא דאינו נשקל בליטרה *lav lemeimra deeino nishkal belitra*? Doesn't
that prove that you're not allowed to sell the meat out in
cut in steaks?
Because if that were true then it would mean that that it
has a lower level קדושה Kedusha. *kedusha* if it develops the מום
*mum*, not that it retains some some of the holiness of the
מום *mum*. רב הונא Rav Huna ורבי חזקיה תלמידי דרבי ירמיה אמרי,
so רב הונא and רבי חזקיה Rabbi Chizkiya
who were the students of רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiya said, so מי
דמי התם שתי קדושות ושני גופין? mi dami hatam shtei kedushot u-shnei
gufin?
In that case we're talking about two different levels of קדושה, right?
One is an animal which is a בכור and one is not,
and שני גופין shnei gufin and two different animals. הכא שתי קדושות
וגוף אחד. Hacha shtei kedushot ve-guf echad. And here we're talking about
שתי קדושות, shtei kedushot, two different statuses in one animal. So if
you look at what רש"י Rashi says, שתי קדושות הן וגוף אחד,
shtei kedushot hen veguf echad, קדושת בכור וקדושת בדק הבית, Kedushat Bechor
u-Kedushat Bedek HaBayit, that is what we've done is you've now talking
about a case where you designated a בכור animal to be בדק
הבית. Bedek HaBayit? So that's trying to infuse the same animal with
two different levels of קדושה. So maybe there's a difference there and
we should distinguish between them. So מתקיף לה רבי יוסי בר אבין.
matkif la Rabbi Yosi bar Avin. רבי יוסי בר אבין Rabbi Yosi
bar Avin pushes back, מה אילו אמר הפדו לי בכור שהתפיסו לבדק
הבית כלום שומעין לו? ma ilu amar hifdu li Bechor she-hitpiso le-Bedek
HaBayit klum shomin lo? So if somebody said, go and redeem me
my בכור that I have donated to בדק הבית, Bedek HaBayit. then
we don't listen to him.
I was going to say, how can he do that?
Well, so we've said this whole time is you were תופס, topes,
if you, if you did it, התפיס בכור לבדק הבית מהו? What,
what is the ruling regarding this בכור that you donate to בדק
הבית? Bedek HaBayit But here, if he says, if go, he says
go redeem for me my בכור, which we said you're not allowed
to do, אין שומעין לו. ein shomin lo. You're not, you don't
listen to him cause you're not allowed to redeem. Cause what is
he trying to do? He is trying to save the בכור from
being a קרבן. Korban, So he's trying to figure out a way
to claim that you should be able to go and be פודה
it, but in fact probably wasn't בדק הבית. Bedek HaBayit So הפדו
רחמנא, hifdo Rachmana,
as if to say, you say back to him like that God
should redeem it for him. So אמר לא תיפדה, amar lo tipadeh,
right? God said you're not allowed to be פודה it. So אלא
אמר רבי אמי. ela amar Rabbi Ami. רבי אמי Rabbi Ami says,
כלום הקנה זה, klum hikne ze,
he doesn't acquire anything, אלא מה שקנו לו. ela ma shekanu lo.
That is that the בדק הבית Bedek HaBayit. doesn't really acquire the
בכור because it has the קדושת בכור, because it's supposed to be
a קרבן, Korban the בדק הבית Bedek HaBayit is not, right, you
can't donate a תם tam animal which is going to be a
קרבן to בדק הבית. That's sort of the whole problem here. So
the issue we're talking about is what if I donated a בכור
to בדק הבית and it developed a מום? And at that point
then the question was still how do you, how do you deal
with the meat? But that is going back on, so there was
the attempted proof from our משנה but it seems like our משנה
is inconclusive because our משנה was talking about at the time when
it was a בכור was intermixed with these other animals was when
it was still a תם. tam. So you have to wait until
it gets a מום and even after it gets a מום then,
then you deal with the meat in the other way. Yeah.
I don't know if we mentioned this or not. So when we're
talking about according to בית שמאי we, and then they had, you
know, this list. Yeah. Then in the notes here it says בית
הלל Beit Hillel hold that a blemished בכור may be eaten by
any טמא tamei person and even a non-כהן.
Right, so there are different ways.
It's חולין, isn't it? Right. They didn't, they didn't mention בית הלל.
Beit Hillel.
Right, it's not mentioned here explicitly. It comes up in the גמרא
Gemara in בכורות. Bechorot. So this סוגיא sugya has a parallel in
בכורות דף ל"א. Bechorot daf lamed-aleph. We'll get there in a few
years, something like that. In a year and a half? Yeah,
about a year and a half. בכורות, Bechorot,
there's a lot of things in בכורות Bechorot that you wouldn't expect
and there are a lot of things in ערכין Arachin that you
wouldn't expect. So we'll certainly have a lot of fun. ערכין Arachin
is a wild מסכת. masechet. ערכין Arachin has all sorts of things.
We have a little bit of סוגיא sugya left to do before
the next משנה. Okay.
So the גמרא Gemara says, the last line in the משנה, הכל
יכולין להתערב, ha-kol yacholin le-hitarev, anything can get mixed up and we
sort of know how to resolve the mixture except for חטאת ואשם.
Chatat ve-Asham. So מאי שנא חטאת ואשם, mai shna Chatat ve-Asham, דהאי
זכר והאי נקבה? de-hai zachar ve-hai nekeva? So maybe you'll say that
the reason why is because חטאת ואשם Chatat ve-Asham are usually female
animals and the other קרבנות Korbanot are usually male animals. Not necessarily
true but at
least... חטאת ועולה נמי. Chatat ve-Ola nami. So חטאת Chatat and עולה
Ola you could also say that is because the עולה Ola could
also be, no, עולה Ola has to be a male animal. Right?
Yeah. Yeah, an עולה Ola is a male.
Oh oh fine, אשם is male and חטאת Chatat is female. That's...
חטאת ואשם Chatat ve-Asham cannot mix together. That's, sorry I misunderstood. Okay.
Right right. So חטאת ואשם, Chatat ve-Asham, a
personal חטאת Chatat is always... A personal חטאת Chatat is
always female and קרבן אשם Korban Asham which is always personal is
always a male animal. Sorry. So you said, so we say how
can they not mix together, דהאי זכר והאי נקבה. de-hai zachar ve-hai
nekeva. So חטאת ועולה נמי. Chatat ve-Ola nami. So then you should
say the חטאת and עולה Ola also can't mix because the עולה
Ola also has to be male and the חטאת would have to
be female. Right. So איכא שעיר נשיא. ika se'ir nasi. No, the
קרבן חטאת Korban Chatat brought by the נשיא, Nasi, by the king
or by whomever, has to be a male animal as well, so
you could imagine a case where חטאת נשיא Chatat Nasi was mixed
up with the קרבן עולה Korban Ola and then you wouldn't know
which one was which. So האי שיער והאי צמר. hai se'ar ve-hai
tzemar. But goats have hair and sheep have wool.
That is, you'd still be able to tell the difference between sheep
and goats. So פסח ואשם למה לא מתערב? Pesach ve-Asham lama lo
mitarev? And for that reason, קרבן פסח Korban Pesach which could be
brought from either sheep or... or goats and the קרבן אשם *korban
asham* which has to be brought from a sheep a ram
then נמי לא מערב
*nami lo me'arev* you would say that they also can't be mixed
together. So האי בן שנה והאי בן שתי שנים *hai ben shana
vehai ben shtei shanim* and also because of the age. קרבן פסח
*korban Pesach* has to be one year old or less than one
year old and the קרבן אשם *korban asham* has to be in
its second year. So איכא אשם נזיר ואשם מצורע *ika asham nazir
ve'asham metzora*. So אשם נזיר *Asham Nazir* and אשם מצורע *Asham Metzora*
could be younger. Those are exceptions not like an אשם אשם ודאי
*asham asham
vadai* not the cases of אשם תלוי *asham talui*. אשם תלוי *Asham
Talui* has to be an older animal. אשם גזילות *Asham Gezeilos* has
to be older animal but אשם נזיר *Asham Nazir* and אשם מצורע
*Asham Metzora* could be younger. ואיבעית אימא *ve'iba'is eima* alternatively you could
say איכא בן שנה דמיחזי כבן שתי שנים *ika ben shana demichzei
k'ven shtei shanim*. You could have a one year old animal which
is very mature which looks like a two year old animal ואיכא
בן שתי שנים דמיחזי כבן שנה *ve'ika ben shtei shanim demichzei k'ven
shana*. You could have a two year old animal which looks like
a one year old animal.
Or you may have lost the record of
the but you that's the whole thing is that animals are not
counted from their birthday. They're counted from whatever either ראש חודש אלול
*Rosh Chodesh Elul* ראש חודש תשרי *Rosh Chodesh Tishrei* because we sort
of just have to with animals we don't care about birthdays. We
just care about how also because they're more or less born around
the same time all of them. They have a mating season and
they have a birthing season. So the animals are all roughly the
same age per
per class right. Okay anyway we'll stop there. Hope everyone has a
wonderful day and Rabbi Linzer go to the דף *daf*? We could
let's we could read the משנה *mishna* at least. Let's read the
משנה *mishna*. I don't want to go too far either because then
we'll get too far ahead and then we'll mess up the whole
whole idea of דף יומי *Daf Yomi* is to do a דף
*daf* per day. Okay the משנה *mishna* says אשם שנתערב בשלמים *Asham
shenisarev bishlamim*. What if a קרבן אשם *korban asham* was mixed up
with שלמים *Shelamim*? There are certain ways in which they have an
affinity to each other but also not. So רבי שמעון אומר שניהם
ישחטו בצפון ויאכלו כחמור שבהן *Rabbi Shimon omer shenehem yishchatu batzafon veyo'chalu
kechamur shebahen*.
You have to shecht both of them in the צפון *tzafon* in
the north of the מזבח *mizbe'ach* like is required for the אשם
*asham* but is not required for the שלמים *shelamim* and ויאכלו כחמור
שבהן *yo'chalu kechamur shebahen* and you have to eat them like the
most severe that is that it has to be eaten only by
כהנים *kohanim* like the קרבן אשם *korban asham* and not by the
owners like the קרבן שלמים *korban shelamim*.
And in the עזרה *Azara*. And in the עזרה *Azara*.
So אמרו לו *amru lo* they say back to him אין מביאין
קדשים לבית הפסול *ein mevivin kodashim l'veis hapsul*. The problem is if
you bring an animal which which could be eaten by many people
and you reduce the number of people who are allowed to eat
it that is you took a קרבן שלמים *korban shelamim* and now
you're saying that only כהנים *kohanim* are allowed to eat it aren't
you bringing it לבית הפסול *l'veis hapsul* because it's going to end
up being נותר *nosar*? You're going to run out of time to
eat it there'll be fewer people who are allowed to eat it
right שלמים *Shelamim* also has a longer period of time that you
can eat it two days and one night as opposed to one
day and until midnight. Okay so so this is the objection to
the opinion of רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon*. נתערבו חתיכה בחתיכה *Nisarvu chaticho
bechaticho* what if pieces of meat which were already cut up got
mixed together or קדשי קדשים בקדשים קלים *kodshei kodashim b'kodashim kalim* or
those קרבנות *korbanos* which are only eaten by כהנים *kohanim* were mixed
up with those which are even allowed to be eaten by ישראלים
*yisraelim*. הנאכלין ליום אחד בנאכלין לשני ימים *Hane'echalin l'yom echad b'ne'echalin l'shnei
yamim* or קרבנות *korbanos* which are only eaten for one day were
mixed with two days like imagine a קרבן פסה *korban Pesach* was
mixed up with with a קרבן שלמים *korban shelamim* or or something
like that which I imagine could happen regularly on פסה *Pesach*. שני
ימים ולילה אחד ויאכלו כחמור שבהן *shnei yamim velaila echad yo'chalu kechamur
shebahen*. You have to eat them like the strictest level that is
we apply the principle of רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* and it sounds
like the objection of the חכמים *chachamim* somehow doesn't seem like it
has much teeth. The claim is אין מביאין קדשים לבית הפסול *ein
mevivin kodashim l'veis hapsul* you can't let them get into a situation
where where they'll end up being disqualified. But for חתיכות *chatichos* which
have already been shechted and already had the זריקות *zrikos* and have
already been cut up you're sort of stuck at that point. It's
not like a living animal that you can decide whether or not
to bring the קרבן *korban*. Here they've already been cut up so
so the חכמים *chachamim*'s objection to רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* doesn't really
stand and certainly it seems like רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon*'s opinion makes
a certain amount of sense which is that we have relatively little
reason to be so concerned about נותר *nosar*. Of all the other
things here we're talking about whether the קרבן *korban* is going to
end up doing what it's supposed to do and you're telling me
you're worried about some future concern of נותר *nosar* maybe it's not
such an issue. Okay we'll stop here. Hope everyone has a wonderful
day. יישר כח *Yiyasher koach*. And Rabbi Linzer will pick up with
the גמרא *gemara* starting at the bottom of ע"ה עמוד ב' *ayin
hay amud beis* tomorrow.
Can I ask
you a question?